<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A worthy practise of the moste learned phisition Maister Leonerd Fuchsius, Doctor in phisicke, moste necessary in this needfull tyme of our visitation, for the comforte of all good and faythfull people, both olde and yonge, bothe for the sicke and for them that woulde auoyde the daunger of the contagion</title>
            <author>Fuchs, Leonhart, 1501-1566.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01285</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844303</idno>
  <idno type="VID">9102</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240886506</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 11408</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S108646</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99844303e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01285)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9102)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 544:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A worthy practise of the moste learned phisition Maister Leonerd Fuchsius, Doctor in phisicke, moste necessary in this needfull tyme of our visitation, for the comforte of all good and faythfull people, both olde and yonge, bothe for the sicke and for them that woulde auoyde the daunger of the contagion</title>
                  <author>Fuchs, Leonhart, 1501-1566.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[28] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Rouland Hall, for Michell Lobley in Poules Churchyeard at the corner shop on the right hand as ye come oute of Chepe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1563]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A regiment for the plague.</note>
                  <note>Leaves Av and Biiii missigned Bv.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B(-B7-8).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Sweating-sickness --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9102:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9102:1"/>
            <p>A worthy pra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctise of the moste learned Phisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>Maister Leonerd Fuchsius,</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor in Phisicke, moste necessary in this needfull tyme of our visitation, for the comforte of all good and faythfull people, both olde and yonge, bothe for the sicke and for them that woulde auoyde the daunger of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Roland Hall, featuring a boy with wings upon his right arm and with his left hand holding, or fastened to, a weight (McKerrow 142)</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>PRINTED AT LONDON</hi> by Rouland Hall, for Michell Lobley in Poules Churchyeard at the corner shop on the right hand as ye come oute of Chepe.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="medical_treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:9102:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9102:2"/>
            <head>A Regiment for the Plague, takene out <hi>of Fuchsius.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F there appeare certaine and manifest signes of the plague (if nothinge elles maye let it) then straight waye muste the Pacient be let bloode in that syde where the rysyng or gathering is. If it be about the chinne or any other parte of the face or necke, blood muste runne by the shoulder vayne, the which Phisitions cal <hi>Cepalica,</hi> (as that which appertaineth vnto the head) in the same syde. If it be in the arme pittes, then the inner vayne of the arme, whiche belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to the Lyuer or Mealte of man must be smitten, or the myddle vayne, if the other appere not. If the soore be in the twysell or groyne, then bloode must be let in the Ancle of the same syde. If
<pb facs="tcp:9102:3"/> there appere no rising: then in the same side where greatest grefe is felt. But in what maner of veyne, the sorenes of the parts greued, shall shewe &amp; declare. For if the parts aboue the stomacke be most greued &amp; afflicted then the sholder veine if the partes beneath the necke be more molested &amp; troubled the inner or middel vein of the arme, but the baser parts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing most annoied, then the veine in the hāme or ancle must be smitten. And if y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> strength of the patient be lustye, bloude must be drawen aboundantly, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion obserued that wise surgeans cā well limite.<note place="margin">Boring.</note> If that for age, or otherwyse we may not vse letting bloud, let y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> neck yet, or the shoulders, or the backe, or the thighes be bored after y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> maner as was prescribed in smitting the veines. If at meale the stomacke being full thys di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sease doe take the, strayte waye thou muste vomite.<note place="margin">Vomite.</note> The bodye then beynge thus by these euacuate and disburdened some medicyne we muste take that is a repeller of poyson,<note place="margin">Preserua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues.</note> to the ende it maye drawe
<pb facs="tcp:9102:3"/> poyson vnto it, and remoue it frome the harte. For thys is as Galene witnes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth in the fyfte booke of the powers of symple medicamentes the action and proper doynge of medicynes that resiste and wythstande poysons. Amonge o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of thys kynde whyche be in deede manye, the electuarye, called <hi>electuari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um de ouo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Electua de ouo.</note> is speciallye praysed, an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectuarye vnto the good Apothecaries not vnknowen. Why I doe preferre thys almoste before all other the woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull effecte and power thereof hath caused, the whyche it hath often times shewen in manye pacientes, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it is easye to be gotten, and hathe trewe and lawefull symples that goe to the composition thereof, sauynge the roote of <hi>Dictamnus albus,</hi> in steade wherof better it is to take the leaues of true <hi>Dictanmus,</hi> or in stede of it Sage. Of thys electuarye is gyuen to theym that are growen to strengthe by yeares the weyght of one dramme.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9102:4"/>
            <p>But for the yonger two thyrdedeales of a Dragme do suffice. But it muste be dissolued in the water of Roses, or of Endiue, or of Scabiose. The vse also of this medicine is not to be neglected in preseruing, if dayly you take thereof the weyght of one grayne, or of two Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley graynes, or the quantitie of a Pease. The takyng of this Potion also doeth much good.<note place="margin">A Potion.</note> Take of Andromachus triacle two thyrdedeales of Dragme, of Mithridation one thyrdedeale of a Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gme, of Bole armeniake preparate half a thyrde deale of a Dragme, of rose wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Scabiose, and Buglosse water, of eche an vnce.</p>
            <p>Howe great vertue there is in Bole-armeniake<note place="margin">Bole Arme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niake.</note> to dryue away the Plague, Galene in his nynth booke of the facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of simple medicaments doth abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dauntly declare, who writeth that in a great Pestilence which waxed cruell at Rome, all that euer dranke of this Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion were soone recured. Wherefore in plague tyme of this there woulde bee
<pb facs="tcp:9102:4"/> muche vse. The pouder that next folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth in Fuchsius because these other two medicines be of so great efficacie, I omit as not necessarye. Some one therefore of the two former beinge ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, let the diseased partye bee lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in bedde, well heate wyth some Scaldabetto in soft shetes, and well co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered with clothes, that there he maye sweate<note place="margin">Sweate.</note> foure or fyue houres as hys strength maye beare. If that this waye sweate wyll not come, heate Tyles or Brickestones in the fyer, and laye to the soles of his feete. For they with speede wyll cause a sweating. But in all the tyme of the sweate, we muste take dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent héede that the party neither sleepe, eate, nor drynke. After this sweate,<note place="margin">What after sweate must be done.</note> let the Pacient be wyped with cleane lyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen clothes. Then if he will and can let him arise out of his bedde keping in, for that tyme in the same chamber. But let the chamber foure or fyue tymes a daye be amended and purged with fragrant and swéete smelling things.<note place="margin">The emen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the ayre.</note> Good it is
<pb facs="tcp:9102:5"/> to change chambers in the continuance of his syckenes, bycause the ayre of one chamber beyng corrupt by the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce of the pacient cānot easely be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered. And let the chamber whyther he goeth be fyrst perfumed. Of what sorte the perfumes ought to be, we will after<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward declare. After sweate two or three houres,<note place="margin">When meat must be gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</note> offer the patient the broothe of some pullet as he shalbe able to beare it, &amp; let it be often times don. For he must be strengthened by litle &amp; litle. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is good for him often to eate, but yet very litle. And such as ar thus mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted shall soner recouer then other. He may also eate the fleshe of pullettes boi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> sorell sance,<note place="margin">Wherewith we must kepe him waking.</note> or the iuice of limons, or vergrise. The pacient also y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> first daye must be kept frō slepe w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> talke, or exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, or noise, or w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> rubbing y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> eares or nofe or w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> pulling by the heare.<note place="margin">His drinke.</note> To thys purpose it shall not be absurde to put vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to his nostrels a spong dipped in stronge vinaigre. In his greate thyrste you may vse this potion, whiche hath of the iulep
<pb facs="tcp:9102:5"/> of Violettes three vnces, of the serape of the sower iuyce of Citrones one vnce, and a halfe, of the serape of endyue two vnces, of the Licour that sorell, scabiose, and the flowers of Borage hathe beene boiled in tenne vnces, or as muche of their waters. Lette these thynges be mingled and made a drynke. You maye also wyth water that a lytle barley hath bene boyled in, myngle the iuyce of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, or of sorel, or of Limons, or vergrise and gyue it as a drynke, or the same in small ale for the Barley water.<note place="margin">Medicamen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes that strengthen.</note> But yf there be weakenes we muste minister suche medicamentes as can strenghen and comfort the hart and the other parts that beare the dominion in oure bodye. Such a potion is that that taketh of con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>serue of Vyolettes, Roses, and buglosse of eche an vnce and a halfe of Bole Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menick preparate a Dramme, of redde Corall a thyrdeeale of a Dramme, of the ryne of Citron a Dramme and a halfe, of Camphyre a Dramme or two thirdedeales with y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> tart iuyce of pome<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>citrons
<pb facs="tcp:9102:6"/> sufficient, let there be made a moyste preseruatiue against poyson. Vpon the place of the heart also, if the the Pacient feele an heate aboute the stomack, you muste ley this to lenge on. Take of Rose, of Buglosse, and Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell water, of eche foure vnces, of the spyces of the preseruatiue of precious stones, that is to witte, of Ben bothe whyte and red, of Cloues, Ginger, long Pepper, Spikenarde, of folner Saffron and Graynes, or rather of Cardomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum, of eche a Dragme, of the woode of Aloe, of red Sanders, of the ryne of Pomecitrone beaten into pouder, of the bone of the Stagges hart, of eche a third deale of a Dragme. All this being min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled together let there be made a Plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster. But we muste take heede that we laye it not on but being heate by some fyer. After that it waxeth colde, it muste strayght way be taken awaye. For then it stoppeth the pores, and doeth great annoyaunce vnto the Pacient. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore better it is to vse Bagges<note place="margin">Bagges.</note> called
<pb facs="tcp:9102:6"/> Cordials for helping the hart, suche as this is. Take of the flowers of red Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, of whyte water Lilies, of Violetts, of all two Dragmes, of all the Saun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, of whyte &amp; red Corall, of Spodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, and Pearle, of eche thre Dragmes, of Cinomum, Cloues, of the bone of the Stagges heart, of the woode of Aloe, of the ryne of Pomecitron, of Saffron, of eche a thyrde deale of a Dragme, of the seede of Sorrell, two thyrde deales, of Purselane seede foure graynes.</p>
            <p>All these thinges beyng beaten to pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, let there be made square bagges of silke, and stemmeale, let them be layed to whote. In fine,<note place="margin">The cures for peculier places.</note> we muste diligently take heede, that poysoned humours bee drawen to the place where the grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes do ryse by boxings, or other medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that hath the facultie to drawe, as is this that hath of Figges sixe, of Raisins halfe an vnce, of salt called Sal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gemma, two Dragmes, of Honnye, an vnce, with the oyle of Camomille, let there be made a plaister,<note place="margin">A plaister.</note> the which must
<pb facs="tcp:9102:7"/> be laide on whote vppon the grefe, other els in steade of that, suche one whyche is much commended of all men.<note place="margin">Another plai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ster.</note> Take the greatest onion that you cā get and pare away the crowne holowing it, and fill it w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> Andromachus triacle, addinge there to the iuyce of Rue and Sage. Then stoppe the crowne with clay &amp; rost it wel When it is sufficientlye rosted braye it in a morter vntyll it be lyke a salue, and laye it vppon the place affected. Thys playster is also very fytte for the ripinge Take of the meale of Fengreeke, of Lyne seede, and of the flowers of camo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mylle, of eche halfe an vnce, of the roote of Marrishe or water malowes,<note place="margin">Another plai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ster to rype he sore.</note> and of white Lilyes, of eche thrée Drammes, of Fygges fixe, of the leafe of true <hi>Dic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamnus</hi> thrée Drammes of the roote of Valerian twoo Drammes of Senuie seede one Dramme and the halfe, of pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons dunge halfe an vnces, of the oiles of Lylyes, and Camomylle, of eche one vnce and a halfe. Let these thynges be
<pb facs="tcp:9102:7"/> wrought into the fourme of a plaister or pultes and vsed.<note place="margin">Another.</note> Thys salue is also much praysed. Take of the salue called <hi>Dia chilon</hi> the symple twoo vnces, of Ammoniake, and Galbanum, of eche one vnce. Beate these togither &amp; make a salue. But yf wyth these foremore the sore breaketh not, then take gose dunge and temper it wyth salate oyle or wyth oile of Camomille.<note place="margin">Preseruing from the plague Auoyding is surest.</note> Let this suffise for the curynge of suche as are taken wyth the plague. Nowe howe one maye preserue hymselfe from the plague that infesteth any one place we wyll declare. Syth the plague is not ingendred but by feachynge in by breathynge a pesty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and rotten ayre: certayne it is that there is no remedye more presente then auoydynge. For there is no meane to be quyte oute of the pesty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lente ayre, excepte we go vnto some place where the ayre is not vitiate and corrupte.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9102:8"/>
            <p>The which thing is so muche the moore spedily to be done, as this mischiefe is contagious and daungerous for infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as dayly experience doth shewe.</p>
            <p>We muste auoyde also farre of, that is to witte, into some place where we know that the ayre is yet pure. Neither must we retourne home, but with good leasure. Wherefore the people is wont to saye, that there is more helpe in these thre wordes, Some, Farre, and Late, then in three Apoticaries shoppes right wel instructed and trimmed. Wherfore they who for their functions and offices maye commodiously, let them not staye in the corrupt ayre. If they do they shal basarde them selues with the daunger. For (as Galene testifieth writing vnto Piso of Triacle) the Plague as a sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uage beast strayeth and slayeth not few, but some tyme euen whole cities. For a certaine euil chaunge of the ayre vnto corruption is sodden, and men, when by necessitie of breathe fetching there, they can not auoyde the peryll, do drawe into
<pb facs="tcp:9102:8"/> them by the mouth the ayre, as a certain poyson. Wherefore (sayeth Galene) I must needes prayse Hippocrates a man praise worthy for many causes, whiche depelled the plague that inuaded Grece out of Ethiopia, by none other meanes than by chaunging and altering the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stitution of the ayre, that suche and the same mighte no moore be breathed.</p>
            <p>When therefore he had commaunded fyer to be made thorowe all the citie of Athenes, he aduised not them to burne woode only, but to cherishe the fier with Garlands and flowers, and sweete her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes dryed, and to caste on fatte and fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant incenses, that men might drawe breath depured by this meane. Thus he. This place of Galene haue I reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that all men maye hereby euidently knowe, that the chaunge and alteration of the place by the consent of all the best Phisitions is the speciallest remedie.</p>
            <p>But it is not vnknowen that in thys tyme there be some churlishe men,<note place="margin">Agaynst cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayn precise Diuines.</note> and to full of maners, and verye Stoikes,
<pb facs="tcp:9102:9"/> which crye oute, that the godly and the Christian ought not to feare death, and much lesse to auoide it, &amp; therfore would not y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> we should harken vnto phisitians coūsel. Trimme mē surely, who require that of vs, the which no holy one, no not Christ hymself as man colde-performe, when the scripture doth wytnes him to haue feared death. And y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> good men haue dreadded it, it is no meruale, syth it is en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>graffed in vs by god to defend our lyfe, &amp; to auoyde death. Therefore Paule wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the Ephesians the fourth saieth. No man euer hated his owne flesh, but rather nourisheth, &amp; cherisheth it. But y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> saints did feare &amp; shone death, is euident by many exāples of the scripture. Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham for feare of death called Sara hys wife his sister. Iacob fearyng death, fled from hys brother Esau into Mesopota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia. Dauid desyrynge to saue hys lyfe auoyded Saulle and Absalom. The moste stowte and hardye Propheete Elias, when the Prophetes of Baall were slayne,
<pb facs="tcp:9102:9"/> beyng feared with the threateninges of Iesebell the queene fledde into deserte. Moyses, when he was sought for of the king of the Egyptiames, w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> fleeing into Midia prouided both for hym selfe &amp; hys life. But these manerly men will saye, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> these examples do not teach y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> that death that the plague bringeth but that which foloweth persecution ought to be auoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. To whom I aunswere againe that death is deathe of what cause so euer it commeth. God amonge other afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons numbreth famine, the whiche if we may auoyde: why maye we not also the plague? But y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Abraham Isaac, &amp; Iacob auoyded famine is more manifest, then that we nede any longe rehersall therof. If that we may flée no punishementes by god layed vpon vs: then no Christian may eschewe the Turke &amp; other tirānes whom we knowe to be the scourges of god, &amp; therefore do they amisse which for sake townes and vilages when they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proche. With like reason, yf an house be fyred no man shall runne oute to slacke
<pb facs="tcp:9102:10"/> the burning. For no man will deny, but that fire is to be accounted among gods afflictions. Beside this he y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> falleth into the waters, shall not prouide for himself by swimming, but shal suffer with good wyll the waters to take away hys lyfe. Finally anye parte of the body beyng wounded, or bene broken, the Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an shall not require the Surgeons help, for he shall abyde Gods punishment.</p>
            <p>No man with clothing and suche other thinges and meanes, shall defende the colde as being gods crosse. What need manye wordes? No Christian by this reason shalbe so bolde as to vse any kynde of remedie against any kynde of disease, because no kynde of disease is not to be counted amonge Gods visita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. That the godly then maye not feare death is thus to be taken, that they ought not to discourage with the feare of death, and commit synne to auoyde it, and in death to dispaire. For there are bookes of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> best diuines of our time Martine Luthere, &amp; Brentius, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with
<pb facs="tcp:9102:10"/> the dreames of suche Stoikes are refuted, whose iudgementes I set more by then by an hundred others. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I let passe these &amp; such other obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of these dreamers, &amp; returne vnto my purpose. If that by iuste and lawful causes thou maiest not eschew the place then do thy diligence, that thy house wherein thou must abide be voide of all stench filth and brutture. Let the wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes of the same be closed, &amp; specially in closse &amp; rayny daies, that the pestilent aire enter not. But if thou wilt opē any let them be toward the easte or y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> North and let it be done when the sun is some what highe. Seldome, and not but in fayre weather muste we come abroade, but not wythoute a preseruatiue taken before, whyche maye conserue from contagion. In the house daylye we muste kyndle fyre wyth Oken woode or Iunypere or galle, or Baie or suche lyke wherewyth the ayer maye be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended and purged.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9102:11"/>
            <p>For that the powre of fire is meruelous to recure the rottenes of the aire we are sufficiently tought by. Hippocrates ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample that I declared a lytle before.<note place="margin">Perfumes,</note> Vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pon liue coles also cast this pouder often which hath of rosemary half an handful of Sage, Betonie, wormewoode, Maio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram, organe, of eche an handfull dry thē and beate thē to pouder. Or this. Take of Iunipere beries an vnce. of Mirrhe. 3. drammes, of Frankensence, &amp; Masticke of eche .3. drammes and the halfe, of the roote of benedicta a dramme, of rue half an vnce, of the barke of Cipres a drāme of angelike and Lauander of eche twoo drammes breake them togither &amp; make a pouder. Let the poore lay vpon the coles Iunipere wood hewen or y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> beries them selues. Richer men may vse the wood of Aloe or the pouder of Gallia moschata, of cloues, or of such like. When needes you must abroad, cary w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> you other thys or some like pomander whiche hathe of Labdanum. 3, drammes, of storax cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mita, two drammes, of Cinomū, macis
<pb facs="tcp:9102:11"/> Cloues, Nuttemigs of eche a dramme, of the woode of Aloe, a thirdedeale of a dramme of spikenarde half a thirddeale of a Dramme, of Mirrhe Mastiche fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kensence half a dramme, of Muske, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, of ech .3. graines, let these be moisted after beating &amp; renging in so much stact and Maioram water as maye suffice, &amp; make therof a ball to smell to. In sōmer let y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> aire in house be bettered with cold thinges, that is to witte, w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> Roses, Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lettes, water lilies, vine leaues: wilowe leafes &amp; such other. Moiste also the paue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of the house, with Rosewater, or Sorell water, &amp; such like, or w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> cold wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter mingled with a litle Vinaigre. It is good also to smel Roses, vinaigre, Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyre, sanders, &amp; other of such sort, or els haue this ball to sauour. Take of Lab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danum half an vnce, of storax calamita 3. drammes, of the floures of white wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter lilies, Roses, violets of eche a drāme of the barke of pome Citron a dramme &amp; a half, of al the sanders, of eche, halfe a Dramme of Maces &amp; Cinamom, of eche
<gap reason="missing" resp="#oxf" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:9102:12"/> Ye must vse cleane sheetes reposed &amp; sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uored, a while with some swete odours. After slepe when y<seg rend="sup">u</seg> risest, prouide first to purge &amp; disburden thi body and specially take hede that at anye tyme the belly be not bound. And therfore if by it self daily it be not disburdened take the Pylles y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> are called <hi>Pillulae Rufi,</hi> or some soft cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, or some supposiitorie prepared ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. When the body is clensed from su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluite bothe by belly &amp; bladder, some medicine must be taken y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> may defende vs from the contagion of the sickenes wherof we wil declare many hereafter, And if for necessarie busines thou must nedes abrod, thou shalt eate zedoarie, or the roote af Pimpinell, or els shalt smell Rue. For the smell of it meruelously re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisteth the corrupt aire. Venus muste be none or moderate. Publik hote house as most present poysons are to be detested, because by the heate of them the pores beyng open, the pestilent aire most redi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perseth into the inmost partes of the bodye. Who will vse priuate bath, after
<pb facs="tcp:9102:12"/> the issue out of the same, let him most diligently defend himselfe from the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt aire. Better it is to vse at home fric<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiones, that is rubbinges &amp; wypings in good aire then any bathes. You must yet washe the head wéekely w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> lye wherein Maioram, Lauander, Rosemary, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonie, Sage, Camomille, &amp; suche other hath bene boiled.<note place="margin">Letting blod</note> But lustye yonge men who abound w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> bloude, in plague time must vse letting of blood, &amp; that not once if nothing els do let but againe &amp; againe which hath in it a special helpe to defend the health, because it cooleth the habite of the body, &amp; bringeth it to commodera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of heate.<note place="margin">Purgation.</note> We must purge our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies also w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> purgations if the thing so re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quire, &amp; that principally in springtime, &amp; in autume, as Hippocrates willeth. Now for our affectiones, sorow, angre,<note place="margin">Afflictions of minde.</note> batred, feare, greuous cares, &amp; all pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siue thoughtes must be auoyded.<note place="margin">Medicins t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> preserue. Rufus pyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les.</note> Nowe remaineth there to go foreward to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> preserue emonge the whiche be Rufus pilles which be called the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon
<pb facs="tcp:9102:13"/> pilles or pils for the plague. Take of Aloe iecoraria two parts, of Saffron and mirrhe, of eche one part, &amp; with sca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biose water, or white wyne make youre pilles, whereof daylye take one thyrdedeale of a Dramme or a lytle more or lesse accordyng as age and strength re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth. Although shoppes doe call this cōposition Rufus pils: yet is it different fro y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> that Rufus once prescribed. But these pilles which the shoppes do vse, for the Aloe and mirrhe that much do with stande putrefaction, haue great efficacie againste the infection of the plague and therefore ar not to be neglected. We maye also often vse the pylles whyche haue of Aloe iecoraria three drammes, of Myrrhe one dramme and a half, of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garike prepate one Dramme, of Saf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron halfe a Dramme of Bole Arme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niacke preparate one thyrdedeale of a Dramme of the seede of Pome Citron twoo thyrdedeales of a Dramme, of masticke halfe a thyrdedeale, of the rote
<pb facs="tcp:9102:13"/> of Pimpimelle halfe a Dramme, wyth Rose water incorporate these thynges, and make thirtene pilles of one Dragm of the whyche you muste take one or two: You may also vse the electuarye called <hi>Electuarium de mucibus,</hi> the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cription whereof I omitte because it is longe, and bycause the good Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye yf he be demaunded can the compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sityon, or hathe it readye for the helpe of suche times as thys is to releue them that seke vnto hym. Bole Armenye also taken wyth Vinaigre is very much praysed. But bycause Bole is not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer trewe, good it is to take <hi>Terra Lennia,</hi> yf it be good in the steade there of, other elles <hi>Sanguis Draconis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Triacle also, and Mithridatium, and suche other maye to purpose well be taken.</p>
            <p>Thys haue I translated to the cōfort of them that neede counsell, and although
<pb facs="tcp:9102:14"/> all cannot with their ease folow all, yet may they espye the generall way to help this euill. Wherefore as farre forth as thou canst seke the ordinaunces of god in hys creatures, and neglecte not hys meanes, whiche with praier and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendement of life no doubt shall doe and shewe the natures that God hathe created them vnto.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:9102:14"/>
            <head>A prayer.</head>
            <p>ALmightye and eternal god vvhich haste vvorthelye visited vs vvyth sickenes after a penurie for our trespas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, turne from vs (vve besech the) thy vvrathe &amp; indignation that vve moste iustly haue deserued, and let this oure humble submissiō confession praier be meane to procure again thy fauourable mercy, that vvith out anxiete for this thine afflictiō vve maye frely honor and glorifie the in peace and quietnes. Grant this o lord for our mediatour &amp; &amp; aduocate Iesu Christes sake to vvhō vvith the &amp; the holy Ghost be all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, praise, and glorie, for euer. Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>